[music]
Please welcome to the stage the vice
president of research [music] at Google
DeepMind, Benois Schillings.
[music]
>> [music]
>> All right, good morning. Uh this is
really quite exciting to be here and
have a chance to to speak with all of
you. Uh my name is Benois Shellings. I'm
actually a bit of a noob when it comes
to to machine learning. Till a year and
a half ago, I was working for Google X
which some of you may know. We've done
things like Whimo, which seems to be at
every street corner now. Uh we also do
things like Glass. So, you know, we we
had a mix of hit and success. But in
many ways this was for me an interesting
formative experience on how to run a
research team in a place like deep mind.
I do have an incredible team. Uh my team
goal in deep mind is basically to
develop whatever technology will be
needed to make Gemini incredible between
one months and one year from now. So one
month because if you start to work on
what is needed in one week that's a very
different type of job and one year
because I don't think anybody can really
predict anything that far. So that's
already pretty ambitious in my opinion
to think about things that would happen
one year in the future.
We do many things under that role. Uh a
lot of it is related to code which will
be the main subject of my talk today. uh
but we also do a lot of research on what
is the evolution of reasoning for models
for instance or we do topology research
what are new type of network that might
bring better performance uh we do
fundamental work in the science of
reinforcement learning which is so
fundamental to what we're doing today
with ML
let's do a bit of an origin story Um,
we started the project at X named
Pitchfork uh in 2018
which was aimed at looking at how ML
could really improve the way code is
being written. And this was very
interesting because in 2018 when we
presented that at Google honestly nobody
would give us the time of day. uh there
was that point like why would you ever
need ML to to write code. Um at the same
time I think that we totally
underestimated how fast this could go.
When we did that project originally the
idea was to look at how we could speed
up the evolution of a piece of code. How
could we make many of those small
changes which slows down code speed
development? you know the small edit
which requires a review that takes three
days and how we could compress that
cycle.
Some people were talking about vibe
coding writing code in English and at
the time honestly I totally dismissed
that. I was that's why we have
programming language. English is not a
programming language. Well I I guess I
was pretty wrong on that front. But the
resistance we felt at the time reminded
me of how my own career was pretty
resistive to to change. Um I've been
writing code for
45 years. Uh I started by writing video
game for Apple 2 and Commodore 64. So uh
my formation was to write assembly
language. And when you spend a long time
writing assembly language, you look at
compilers with a lot of suspicion,
right? are those things really working
correctly? And then when you switch to
C++ and use compiler, you lose you look
at garbage collected languages as this h
that's not real programming. You need to
manage your memory. Well, today I use
Python and V coding. So even old dogs
can learn new tricks. So uh but I I I do
understand what happened there.
I think that we have a number of eras in
what happened with software and and the
first one was you know the one where I
started writing code where the
fundamental limit was really the machine
and there was a lot of work to go and
extract the last ounce of power out of
those machine and that was the days of
assembly language where you really
needed to be incredibly accurate in the
way you were writing code computing
became much cheaper and we switched to
the modern cloud era where getting the
best performance is not the most
critical aspect. You can actually brute
force many problems but really what
became the limiting factor was the
ability for us to design in a modular
way. You know this was the era where
software was write it only once and this
was this whole idea of how are you going
to build libraries? How are you going to
write functions? How are you going to
break down that problem into something
that is long-term manageable?
The limitation there and that determine
a lot of how our software process are
working where actually the human brain.
Uh a traditional human typical human is
able to get the context between seven
and nine tokens. I mean we have very
rich tokens but you compare that to
modern ML where the context is basically
going to be infinite pretty soon. uh
that fundamental limitation of human
determined a lot of how software was
being written. This is over and we're
switching now to that AI frontier where
really writing the code is not the
challenge anymore. Uh I'll speak some
more about it. But the bottlenecks are
really how do you ensure that that code
is what you really wanted because
writing the code is easy but getting
what is needed for a specific problem
can be much harder to to specify.
So humans at least in the near future
will be that role of architecture or
thinking of what are really the
implication of that piece of code. I'm
getting the ML to to design. Inductive
thinking is another category where I
think humans still have a very clear
edge which is to look at a system in a
much wider context and to be able to
detect patterns and from those pattern
take some decision.
So where are we today? Um, superhuman
syntax generation.
When is the last time I got Gemini to
write a function for me? And I looked at
the function and I was like, I can do
that better.
It's over. Uh, I think that the minutia
of code writing, I mean, you can fight,
you can argue, you can find counter
example, but that time is is gone. Where
we still have a lot of work to do is
multi-step code base. Uh software
engineering is not about writing code.
Software engineering is the first time
you join a company and you realize that
there are 35 million lines of PHP in the
codebase and that you need to make some
changes. That that's the day you
understand what software engineering is
and that's a place where our models
today or frontier models are
progressing. But this ability to manage
that extreme complexity and break it
down into man manageable pieces is a
place where the frontier is still
moving.
Um it goes all the way to architecture.
You look at I don't know the Google
architecture.
Thanks God we have Jeff Dean which was
you know the the key architect there.
But that's the level of thinking which
has many implication which can go from
how do you do hardware optimization? How
do you manage security? How do you build
a system so that 10 years later you're
not full of regrets? And I think this is
really the the range of progress we are
working on today. So code is over but
there's plenty to do. There's plenty of
progress to be made.
Now code is a very unique problem and in
some way that's the reason we we did
pitchfork on this. Um,
first of all, code is a lot of data.
There are other domains where you can
find a lot of data to train your model,
but code was so incredible. You could go
and go on GitHub and start to to scrape
GitHub. So, this was one of those
problem where the amount of training
data was a very unique situation.
It is also a domain where doing
verification is reasonable. You can run
a piece of code, you can compile it, you
can have unit test. So the ability to
figure out is the model generating
something correct was something that was
pretty reasonable to do. That brought us
where we are today. But today what
happened is that we run out of training
data. I think that 80% of the new code
added to GitHub today is machine
generated. So the notion of human
bringing some knowledge that can be used
for mining and to train model is
reaching an end. But the good news is
that we can do selfplay and selfplay is
something we always liked a lot at deep
mind. I suppose all know Alpha Zero.
Alpha Zero became a superhuman go and
chess player without any human knowledge
just by playing against itself. We are
now at that stage where Frontier model
for code are able to do the same where
they can create their own challenge.
They can judge the validity of the
answer. they can even to some extent
judge the architecture. So that ability
to do those hundreds of millions of
hours of selfplay writing code is the
thing that will bring us to the to the
next layer. You know, it's interesting.
Um
do the experiment. Take a a brilliant
software engineer, lock him in a room,
lock him or her in a room for two years
and feed pizza and give the mission you
need to become a better software
engineer. What do you do as a person?
you you give yourself some challenges,
challenges that you can verify and you
keep working and coding on those
challenges. We can do the same here. So
this is an issue of how much compute,
how much selfplay time we can have. But
that will bring the horizon of how far
we go in superhuman coding.
So the economics of code are changing
dramatically. You know, as I say, we
developed a whole software engineering
culture and infrastructure and set of
companies based on the assumption that
writing code was the hard part. That
this was the expensive part. We're now
in a world where writing code is free or
nearly free. That's why I've got the
tilda there.
That means that the amount of code that
we're going to see produced is going to
explode. And there are some hard
implications to that. First is the
question of design and adequacy. How in
front of that mountain of code which
will be written or written dynamically,
how do we keep systems which works and
are reliable at the microscopic level?
Great role for human.
It is also the issue that you know we're
writing code and we're not reading it
very much anymore. I mean I know we
still have code review but I would
predict that in one year we'll let
Gemini or other model generate the code
and nobody will actually look at it. You
know it's similar to compilers who still
check the assembly output of their
compiler and maybe someone there but
that's probably the end of it. So the
same thing is going to happen to code
and that brings some question of what
are the new process that we need to put
in place to keep that manageable
and that's where I've got a
[clears throat] a bit of a list active
guard rails. I mean you've all seen the
news of mythos looking at a piece of
code and detecting a unreasonable number
of vulnerability in that code.
there is a rush to go and patch those
vulnerability but I think that's going
to be a neverending process you know
we're going to get a certain layer of
vulnerability discovered by models we're
going to fix those models will get
smarter they will go a bit deeper and
find even more subtle vulnerability so I
think that the first aspect is that we
need to think at least as much about
code security and the implication of a
piece of code than on the code writing
itself and the grail and you know
something my team is working actively on
is instead of detecting the
vulnerability and then suggesting some
fix how about teaching model to write
correct things from the start
and that is very very hard to do because
it is very context dependent
the other aspect is that you know that's
what I call inductive architecture
uh I think that models today are still
not very good at transferring knowledge
of taking knowledge from one domain and
applying it to another one or taking two
concepts and finding the intersection of
those context to be those context to be
able to do deductive thinking. If we
really want to write those very complex
software system using ML that is a skill
that we need to teach and you know one
aspect of that is to really teach models
how to do correct planning in front of a
problem. How do you look at a very
complex problem and decide what is the
right decomposition of that problem that
will bring the best clarity or
correctness to the to the problem.
We also need to change the way we do
evaluation. I mean u threebench is
infamous in in my book because
threebench
verifies if a piece of code runs and
produce the right output. That's only a
small part of as I mentioned earlier of
code engineering. So for instance, I
think that we need some problems much
more in those benchmarks that we use
which are open-ended problem. I I'll
give an example. Uh I love the question
of text compression. How many bits per
character do you need and how far can
you go? So that's a very simple eval to
to write. You just take a piece of 10
megabyte of code and you tell the model
write the best compressor you can that
is lossless and the loss function in
that case will be you know the size of
the compressed file plus the size of the
source code that's never ending I mean
those problems are I think what's going
to force those model to do novel things
like creating totally new algorithmic
for instance and I I think we're now
getting to that stage
Writing code or doing software
engineering is not thinking as a chain
of tokens.
Thinking and reasoning today is chain of
code which has been you know very
successful and improve models a lot. But
humans of course are much more complex
in the way they think about problems. I
always think that code writing is a very
visual activity and that can be I don't
know the block diagram of what you're
doing or the flow of data through your
code. uh but saying that code will be
just a set of token that you emit that
are going to be the code I think goes
only up to a certain point that's a very
interesting aspect to what we do at
Google Gemini we made that choice from
the onset that this would be a
multimodal model that you know text was
only one of the modality that Gemini
would be able to apply and we're
starting to see you know how can a model
start to think in term of spatial or
dynamic representation to to solve
problem and I think that's going to
become a must have
another interesting question is is this
time to create a new language for models
Python you name it have been invented
for humans and those language are not
very good to write safe or reliable code
I mean they're great to write code but
they're certainly not the the best thing
I think We're getting to the point where
since the pain of writing the code does
not exist anymore. How about we make
writing the code much harder by having
you know very strongly typed languages
or you know some inspiration from lean
on how to write code that by design it's
not going to be perfect. I mean program
proof is something which has some limits
but at least putting the burden of
correctness on the model. So I don't
know if we have some language designers
here, but I I I think there's something
really to be done there and it doesn't
need to be human readable. I I don't
think that that will matter anymore.
So beyond code, um code is a universal
language to solve problems. I think that
what we're starting to see is this
ability to experiment very quickly in
code is impacting other domain very
quickly because doing experiment becomes
basically free. So I think that looking
at that intersection of code writing and
atoms or science is another big front
that we are opening that is the place
where true novelty is going to appear.
two which are especially exciting for me
is chemistry. Um you know as humans we
do not understand chemistry or we
understand a very very small sliver of
chemistry. Once you have more than 20
atoms in your molecule it's like wow we
don't know what that thing is going to
do. I think we're going to see
incredible things emerging out of that.
I mean once you are able to put 10,000
atom together that starts to look like
life. So what are all the other things
you can do with 10,000 atoms?
Biology. You probably heard plenty about
it, but you know, biology is the case of
nature did an incredible engineering job
and terrible job at documentation.
Um, but we can crack through that now.
Models are able to find those
relationship that might be elusive for
us. So I think that that is something
that will open incredible door. And then
there is what I call the gold we cannot
see. Humans are incredibly biased in
what we feel is the correct solution. I
mean, we're the result of an
evolutionary training that help us
survive in the jungle, right? Not doing
quantum computing. So, I think that even
though we can be brilliant and
innovative, there are whole bunch of
progress and breakthrough that can be
done which we just cannot see or
perceive. If I had more time, I would
give some examples. I think that's one
of the thing where ML is such a
different viewpoint on many of those
problems that we're going to get the oh
my god this was in front of us the whole
time and we could not see it. So
exciting times ahead. Thank you very
much. [applause]
>> [music]